A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, European and International Affairs Program (EIA), Office Files of Ruth D. Carter FA1509
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, European and International Affairs Program (EIA), Office Files of Ruth D. Carter
1951-1981, bulk 1968-1980
1968-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Carter, Ruth D.
Ford Foundation
FA1509
1.52 Cubic Feet 4 LTR size Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the staff subject files of Ruth D. Carter, an Assistant Administrative Officer in the Ford Foundation's European and International Affairs Program (EIA). The EIA was situated within the Foundation's International Division. During the time that Carter worked there, it was headed by Craufurd Goodwin and then, starting in 1977, by Francis Sutton. Carter's records are comprised of chronological files that chiefly originate from between 1968 and 1980.
Materials within the chronological files include correspondence, memos, program data reports and lists, and meeting notes. Many of these records document the EIA's support of projects for arms control and international security as well as the study of different regions and peoples in Europe during the time period.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers' papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested as Accession 2019:021.
Biographical / Historical
Ruth D. Carter worked as an Assistant Administrative Officer in the Ford Foundation's European and International Affairs Program (EIA). Throughout her many years in that position, she managed a number of shifting responsibilities. These included the appointment and payment of program consultants, reviewing grantee reports, reviewing drafts of Record Grant Action records, tracking balances for all program appropriations, preparing program management budgets, listing all program actions at the end of each fiscal year, and preparing the program control list.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series. That series is comprised of chronological files. Documents within those files are arranged in reverse chronological order, so the most recent material is at the front of the files.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Chronological files, 1951-1981, bulk 1968-1980
Ford Foundation; Arms Control; Europe; Europe, Eastern; Europe, Western; Europe, Southern; Security, International
- Chronological files, 1951-1981, bulk 1968-1980; 1968-1980; 1; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the chronological files of Ruth D. Carter. Carter created the records through carrying out her different administrative responsibilities in the Ford Foundation's European and International Affairs Program. The correspondence in the files is comprised of letters and memos that were sent between Carter and different EIA program officers, consultants, grantees, support staff, and Program Officers in Charge, Craufurd Goodwin and Francis Sutton. These materials document Carter's duties for reviewing different grant-related records, handling the appointments and payments of program consultants, and compiling and managing different types of data and information for the program.
  The Overseas Development Institute (ODI) and the American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) are amongst some of the grantees that the materials regard. Prominent focus areas of the EIA's grant giving activities during the time that Carter worked as Assistant Administrative Officer include arms control research and the study of different European regions. The series also holds some material regarding the Ford Foundation Paris Field Office which operated from 1970 to 1975. Later records in the series concern the EIA staff's review and discussion of the program's administration as well as possible reorganization of the program.
  - Chronological file, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Chronological file, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Chronological file, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Chronological file, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Chronological file, 1967, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
  - Chronological file, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
  - Chronological file, 1975, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Chronological file, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Chronological file, 1951-1953, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
  - Chronological file, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 24-25)